Guide to the Bilder-Atlas zu Mekka and ephemera (Hisham Khatib Collection) AD.MC.030_ref184
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
Bilder-Atlas zu Mekka and ephemera - Hisham Khatib Collection
Circa 1884-1888
1888
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan)
Haag, M. Nijhoff (1888-1889)
ʻabd Al-Ghaffār, Al-Sayyid
Muḥammad Ṣādiq, Bey,
AD.MC.030_ref184
37 Leaves
Generally good, some brittle and warped.
A partial Bilder-Atlas zu Mekka von Dr. C. Snouck Hurgronje. Herausgegeben von Het Koninklijk Instituut voor Taal-, Land- en Volkenkunde van Nederlandsch-Indië te 's-Gravenhage (Picture Atlas of Mekka by Dr. Christiaan Snouck Hurgronje. Published by the Royal Institute for Linguistics, Land and Ethnology of the Dutch East Indies in The Hague). Imprint Haag: Martinus Nijhoff, 1888. The folio includes photographic and lithographic prints by Muḥammad Ṣādiq Bey (1822 or 1823–1902 or 1903), an Egyptian army engineer who took the first photographs of Medina in 1861 and Mecca in 1880-81 and by al-Sayyid ʻAbd al-Ghaffār (recognised as the first Meccan photographer). Digitized alongside the Bilder-Atlas was the accompanying ephemera including an article entitled How the Mecca pilgrimage is Conducted by A. E. Wort in The Wide World Magazine (1900) and from the March 1937 edition of Life Magazine, The Camera Overseas: Egypt Sends a Carpet to Mecca.
Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184
Content Description
Bilder-Atlas zu Mekka and ephemera
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Photographic Prints; Albumen Prints; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); German Writing; Landscapes; Archaeological Sites/Artifacts; Religious Sites; Pilgrims
- Bilder-Atlas zu Mekka von Dr. C. Snouck Hurgronje. Herausgegeben von Het Koninklijk Instituut voor Taal-, Land- en Volkenkunde van Nederlandsch-Indië te 's-Gravenhage. Picture Atlas of Mekka by Dr. Christiaan Snouck Hurgronje. Published by The Royal Netherlands Institute of Southeast Asian and Caribbean Studies. Imprint Haag: Martinus Nijhoff, 1888., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000001; ʻabd Al-Ghaffār, Al-Sayyid; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000001)
  Mecca (Saudi Arabia); German Writing; Albumen Prints; Printed Materials
- Die Moschee und der nordwestliche Theil der Stadt. 1. Amt des Qâdhî's; 2. Festung auf dem Djèbèl Hindî; 3. Gebäude des Zemzembrunnens; 7. Mimbar (Kanzel); 8. Maqâm èl-Hanafî; 9. Maqâm èl-Mâlikî; 10. Maqâm èl-Hambalî. Die Treppen zur Ka'bah und der Maqâm Ibrâhîm (zugleich Maqâm ès-Schâfi'î) sind hier durch das Zemzemgebäude dem Auge entzogen. The mosque and the northwestern part of the city. The Office of the Qâdhî; 2. Fortress on the Djèbèl Hindî 3. Building of the Zemzem Fountain; 7. Mimbar (pulpit); 8. Maqâm èl-Hanafî; 9. Maqâm èl-Mâlikî; 10. Maqâm èl-Hambalî. The stairs to the Ka'bah and the Maqâm Ibrâhîm (at the same time Maqâm ès-Schâfi'î) are here hidden behind the Zemzem building., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000002; ʻabd Al-Ghaffār, Al-Sayyid; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000002)
  Mecca (Saudi Arabia); The Kaaba/al-kaʿbah (Mecca, Saudi Arabia); Mosques; Architecture; Art; Religious Sites; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; Hand-colored Photographs/Hand-tinting
- Die Moschee.: 1. Das Thor der Benî Schêbah; 2. Das Hidjr; 3. Gebäude des Zemzembrunnens; 4 und 5. Treppen zur Ka'bah; 6. Maqâm Ibrâhîm (zugleich Maqâm ès-Schari'î); 7. Mimbar (Kanzel); 8. Maqâm èl-Hanafî; 9. Maqâm èl-Mâlikî; 10. Maqâm èl-Hambalî; 11. Vorderseite der Hamîdijjah; 12. Die Festung des Djijâd. The mosque. 1. The gate of the Beni Shebah; 2. The hidjr; 3. Building of the Zemzem Fountain; 4 and 5. Stairs to the Ka'bah; 6. Maqâm Ibrâhîm (at the same time Maqâm ès-Schari'î); 7. Mimbar (pulpit); 8. Maqâm èl-Hanafî; 9. Maqâm èl-Mâlikî; 10. Maqâm èl-Hambalî; 11. Front of Hamîdijjah; 12. The fortress of Djijad., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000003; ʻabd Al-Ghaffār, Al-Sayyid; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000003)
  The Kaaba/al-kaʿbah (Mecca, Saudi Arabia); Mosques; Art; Religious Sites; Architecture; German Writing; Hand-colored Photographs/Hand-tinting; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints
- Ein Stück der Kiswah (der brokanten Bekleidung der Ka'bah). ¼ der Originalgrösse. A piece of the Kiswah (the brocade cloth of the Kaaba). ¼ of the original size., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000004; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000004)
  Arabic Calligraphy; German Writing; The Kaaba/al-kaʿbah (Mecca, Saudi Arabia); Photographic Prints; Albumen Prints; German Writing
- Die Ka'bah. The Kaaba., Circa 1881; ref184_000005; Muḥammad Ṣādiq, Bey,; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000005)
  The Kaaba/al-kaʿbah (Mecca, Saudi Arabia); Religious Sites; Mosques; Architecture; Buildings; Pilgrims; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; German Writing; Mecca (Saudi Arabia)
- Othman Pascha mit dem egyptischen Maẖmal. Othman Pasha with the Egyptian Maẖmal., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000006; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); ʻabd Al-Ghaffār, Al-Sayyid; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000006)
  Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Architecture; Buildings; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; Men; Crowds; Pasha; Parades/Processions; Hand-colored Photographs/Hand-tinting; Osman Nuri, Pasha,; German Writing; Political Leadership
- Die von Othman Pascha erbaute Hauptwache (links im Hintergrund èç Çafa). The central police station built by Othman Pasha (left in the background èç Çafa)., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000007; ʻabd Al-Ghaffār, Al-Sayyid; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000007)
  Men; Donkeys; Animals; Architecture; Buildings; Police; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); German Writing; Hand-colored Photographs/Hand-tinting
- Die H̱amīdijjah (von Othman Pascha erbautes Regierungsgebäude). The Hamidiyyah, (The Palace of the Governor built by Othman Pasha)., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000008; ʻabd Al-Ghaffār, Al-Sayyid; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000008)
  Palaces; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Architecture; Buildings; Men; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; German Writing; Street Lamps; Hand-colored Photographs/Hand-tinting
- 'Aun èr-Rafīq, Grossscherif von Mekka (1882– ). Aun èr-Rafīq, Grand sharif of Mecca (1882-)., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000009; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000009)
  Political Leadership; German Writing; Turbans; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Individual Portraits; Medals/Insignia
- Othman Pascha, 1882–86 Generalgouverneur des H̱idjāz .Othman (Nuri) Pasha, 1882-86 General Governor of Hijaz [Hejaz]., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000010; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); ʻabd Al-Ghaffār, Al-Sayyid; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000010)
  Osman Nuri, Pasha,; Men; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Swords/Knives; Weapons; Medals/Insignia; Fez/Tarboush; Carpets/Rugs; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; German Writing; Pasha; Political Leadership; Individual Portraits; Hats
- Thorhüter der Ka'bah. (aus der Schēbah-Familie, die seit vorislamischer Zeit dies Amt innehat). Gatekeeper of the Kaaba (from the Shaybah family who have held this office since pre-Islamic times)., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000011; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000011)
  Men; Individual Portraits; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Turbans; Regional/National Dress; Carpets/Rugs; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; German Writing; The Kaaba/al-kaʿbah (Mecca, Saudi Arabia)
- Vornehmer indischer Kaufmann und türkische Beamte in Mekka. Noble [distinguished] Indian merchant and Turkish officials in Mecca., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000012; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000012)
  Group Portraits; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Men; Turbans; Fez/Tarboush; Regional/National Dress; Weapons; Swords/Knives; Boys; Children; German Writing; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; Medals/Insignia; Hats
- Vornehmner Kaufmann (Bevollmächtigter des Grossscherifs) mit seinem cirkassischen Sklaven. Noble [distinguished] merchant (the representative of the Grand Sharif) with an enslaved Circassian man., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000013; ʻabd Al-Ghaffār, Al-Sayyid; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000013)
  Men; Regional/National Dress; Turbans; Fez/Tarboush; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Prayer Beads; German Writing; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; Group Portraits; Enslavement; Hats
- Muhammad Abd-èl-'Azīz, Sohn des reg. Grossscherifs. Neffe des reg. Grossscherifs. Neffe des reg. Grossscherifs. Neffe des reg. Grossscherifs. Muhammad Abd-èl-'Azīz, son of the reg. Grand sharif. Nephew of the reg. Grand sharif. Nephew of the reg. Grand sharif. Nephew of the reg. Grand sharif., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000014; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000014)
  Boys; Children; Individual Portraits; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; Fez/Tarboush; Uniforms; Swords/Knives; Weapons; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); German Writing; Military/Soldiers; Medals/Insignia; Hats
- Vornehmer Sèjjid in Mekka. Vornehmer Sèjjid in Mekka. Mu'èddin (Aufrufer zum Gottesdienste). Kātib (Schreiber) des Grossscherifs. Noble Sayyid in Mecca. Noble Sayyid in Mecca. Mu'èddin (caller to prayer). Kātib (scribe) of the Great Sheriff., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000015; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000015)
  Men; Individual Portraits; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; German Writing; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Regional/National Dress; Swords/Knives; Weapons; Pens/Inkwells; Carpets/Rugs; Turbans; Political Leadership; Furnishings; Medals/Insignia
- Mekkanischer Arzt. Sohn des Arztes. Kinder aus der Familie der Benī Schēbah (Thorhüter der Ka'bah). Sèjjid in Mekka. Meccan doctor. Son of the doctor. Children from the Benī Schēbah family (Gatekeepers of the Kaaba). Sayyid in Mecca., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000016; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000016)
  Individual Portraits; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; Men; Boys; Carpets/Rugs; Umbrellas/Parasols; Turbans; Regional/National Dress; German Writing; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); The Kaaba/al-kaʿbah (Mecca, Saudi Arabia); Doctors; Officials; Children
- Mekkaner. Kaufleute (Mekka und Djiddah). Ali Rèjjis (aus einem Geschlechte von Obersten der Mu'èddin, welches von Abdallah ibn Zubair herstammen soll). Mu'èddin (Aufrufer zum Gottesdienste). Meccan. Merchants (Mecca and Jeddah). Ali Rjjjis (from a lineage of Colonel Mu'èddin, which is said to come from Abdallah ibn Zubair). Mu'èddin (caller to prayer)., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000017; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000017)
  Men; Individual Portraits; Turbans; Regional/National Dress; Prayer Beads; Carpets/Rugs; Jewelry; German Writing; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; Mecca (Saudi Arabia)
- Mitglieder verschiedener Scherifenfamilien in Mekka. Members of various sharif families in Mecca, Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000018; Snouck Hurgronje, C. (Christiaan); 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000018)
  Men; Individual Portraits; Group Portraits; Swords/Knives; Weapons; Regional/National Dress; Carpets/Rugs; Umbrellas/Parasols; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); German Writing; Albumen Prints; Photographic Prints; Turbans
- Back cover of portfolio: Incorporation of Architects in Scotland. Sir Rowand Anderson Bequest Library., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000019; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000019)
  Libraries; Architecture; English Writing; Scotland, UK; Printed Materials
- Inside cover., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000020; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000020)
  Mecca (Saudi Arabia)
- Back cover., Circa 1884 - 1888; ref184_000021; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000021)
- Article: How the Mecca pilgrimage is Conducted by A. E. Wort in The Wide World Magazine., 1900; ref184_000027; ʻabd Al-Ghaffār, Al-Sayyid; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000027)
  Newspapers/Magazines; English Writing; The Kaaba/al-kaʿbah (Mecca, Saudi Arabia); Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Pilgrims; Printed Materials
- Article: How the Mecca pilgrimage is Conducted by A. E. Wort in The Wide World Magazine., 1900; ref184_000028; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000028)
  Newspapers/Magazines; English Writing; Pilgrims; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); The Kaaba/al-kaʿbah (Mecca, Saudi Arabia); Printed Materials
- Article: How the Mecca pilgrimage is Conducted by A. E. Wort in The Wide World Magazine., 1900; ref184_000029; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000029)
  Newspapers/Magazines; English Writing; Photographic Prints; Pilgrims; Mecca (Saudi Arabia)
- Article: How the Mecca pilgrimage is Conducted by A. E. Wort in The Wide World Magazine., 1900; ref184_000030; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000030)
  Newspapers/Magazines; Pilgrims; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Tombs/Mausoleums; English Writing; Photographic Prints; Religious Sites
- Article: How the Mecca pilgrimage is Conducted by A. E. Wort in The Wide World Magazine., 1900; ref184_000031; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000031)
  Newspapers/Magazines; English Writing; Cairo, Egypt; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Medina (Saudi Arabia); Printed Materials
- Article: The Camera Overseas: Egypt Sends a Carpet to Mecca - Life Magazine., 15 March 1937; ref184_000032; LIFE magazine; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000032)
  Men; Uniforms; Camels; Animals; Newspapers/Magazines; Cairo, Egypt; Fez/Tarboush; Turbans; Photographic Prints; English Writing; Police; Regional/National Dress; Arabic Calligraphy; Flags
- Article: The Camera Overseas :Mecca and its Shrine - Life Magazine., 15 March 1937; ref184_000034; LIFE magazine; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000034)
  Newspapers/Magazines; Mecca (Saudi Arabia); The Kaaba/al-kaʿbah (Mecca, Saudi Arabia); Budapest, Hungary; English Writing; Maps; Architecture; Buildings; Photographic Prints; Coffins/Caskets; Medals/Insignia
- Article: The Camera Overseas: Egypt Sends a Carpet to Mecca - Life Magazine., 15 March 1937; ref184_000035; LIFE magazine; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000035)
  Newspapers/Magazines; English Writing; Street Lamps; Men; Crowds; Camels; Animals; Fez/Tarboush; Parades/Processions; Horses; Regional/National Dress; Railways; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Cairo, Egypt; Photographic Prints; Turbans; Hats
- Article: The Camera Overseas: Egypt Sends a Carpet to Mecca - Life Magazine., 15 March 1937; ref184_000036; LIFE magazine; 1 Photographic Prints (Object Digital copy only: 030_ref184, Object ref184_000036)
  The Kaaba/al-kaʿbah (Mecca, Saudi Arabia); Mecca (Saudi Arabia); Budapest, Hungary; Sheep; Animals; Eid; Children; Boys; Girls; Men; Pilgrims; Architecture; English Writing; Newspapers/Magazines; Group Portraits; Photographic Prints; Railways